<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-21T04:31:33+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nick Moline</title><subtitle>Head of Engineering at Jobscan, Tech Wizard for Harry Potter Lexicon, Community Theatre Sound Designer.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Bonus Action, Two **W**e**A**po**N** Fighting</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/27/two-wan-fighting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bonus Action, Two **W**e**A**po**N** Fighting" /><published>2021-03-27T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/27/dual-wan-at-home</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/27/two-wan-fighting/">&lt;p&gt;Like many people during the pandemic, I’ve been working from home for over a year now, first for Justia, then for Ezoic, and now for Jobscan. One of the reasons I moved to Jobscan was because Jobscan offers me the opportunity to work remotely on a permanent basis. Barbara has also now gotten a job that allows her to work from home, though this may not necessarily be permanent for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing about working from home though, reliable internet is absolutely essential.  If the internet goes down, I can’t reliably work, and neither can Barbara.  Unfortunately, as I’m sure you know, no Internet Service Provider, even a Business ISP, has perfect uptime.  Residential ISPs are even less reliable than business ones, and everyone dreads seeing that “Unable to connect to the Internet” error message when they are trying to get their work done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/chrome-offline.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Unable to connect to the Internet&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;343&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/chrome-offline.png&quot; alt=&quot;Unable to connect to the Internet&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;343&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As internet is essential for the job, one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jobscan.co/careers&quot;&gt;perks&lt;/a&gt; Jobscan offers is a monthly $50 reimbursement to help offset internet costs for employees who are working from home. My original thought when taking the job was “that’s awesome, that’s like half of my internet bill,” but when our ISP had an 8 hour outage one workday, I thought of another idea that would be a better use of that $50, a second broadband internet service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That particular day I used tethering off my phone in order to work, but if this were to happen a lot, tethering was not going to be good enough, especially with both Barbara and myself working remotely. Last week, the internet went down again, this time for 2 whole days, and after it had been down for hours and a tech not able to come till the next day, I decided enough was enough and the time had come to get a backup internet service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In businesses, having multiple broadband internet services is fairly common.  At Justia’s Mountain View Office, there was a time when we had 3 broadband internet services: Cable from Comcast, DSL from AT&amp;amp;T, and a T1 line from Telepacific (we actually had 2 T1 lines from them, but one was entirely voice).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That first day of the 2 day outage, I contacted Cox (the local cable company) and setup service on their $49.99 a month plan (150 megabit download, 15 megabit upload).  This is considerably slower than the Fibre connection I have with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.consolidatedsmart.com/axis-2300&quot;&gt;Consolidated Smart Systems&lt;/a&gt; (940 megabit download, 940 megabit upload), but as a backup connection it will do nicely.  I swung by the local Cox office to pick up a cable modem, brought it home and hooked it up to the previously unused cable jack in the apartment.  For that particular outage, I could just connect to the wifi that comes with the cable modem and use it till my main internet was back up, but I knew that going forward I was going to want a more automated system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business network routers, such as those &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/products/security/adaptive-security-appliance-asa-software/index.html&quot;&gt;popularized by Cisco&lt;/a&gt; often support multiple WAN connections, but it is rare to see a residential network router that could support multiple high-speed internet services at once (&lt;em&gt;some support hooking up a usb cellular internet dongle, but not 2 full fledged broadband services&lt;/em&gt;), in fact I couldn’t find one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of course is that most of these business routers are quite expensive, designed to fill the needs of entire offices they can cost hundreds or even thousands of dollars for a router that will support connecting to multiple internet services and either load balancing connections or handling an automatic failover in the event the primary connection goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could create my own router using a linux box with 3 gigabit network cards, but making one that would robustly handle our connections would still be costly to setup and run. Not sure what I was going to do, I decided to see if I could find an affordable dual-wan router I could setup in my apartment that would handle most of the functionality I needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/tp-link-safestream-multi-wan-router.webp&quot; alt=&quot;TL-R605 SafeStream Multi-WAN VPN Router&quot; width=&quot;3859&quot; height=&quot;2170&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/tp-link-safestream-multi-wan-router.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;TL-R605 SafeStream Multi-WAN VPN Router&quot; width=&quot;3859&quot; height=&quot;2170&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my absolute amazement, I found a router that not only could handle this with 2 WAN connections, but up to 4 WAN connections, while also supporting a lot of the other features typically found in much more expensive business routers, for only &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08QTXNWZ1/&quot;&gt;$59.99 on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tp-link.com/us/business-networking/omada-sdn-router/tl-r605/&quot;&gt;TL-R605 SafeStream Multi-WAN VPN Router&lt;/a&gt; from tp-link is a shockingly good small business router for the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The device has a total of 5 gigabit ethernet ports on it.  The first one is dedicated to the first WAN connection, and the last one is dedicated to a LAN connection.  The remaining 3 ports can be switched between either WAN or LAN depending on your needs allowing connections to up to 4 separate internet providers, which can be setup in a variety of different ways (load balanced, failover, combined) which made it nearly perfect for my setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/TL-R605-ports.webp&quot; alt=&quot;TL-R605 Configurable WAN/LAN ports&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;1000&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/TL-R605-ports.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;TL-R605 Configurable WAN/LAN ports&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;1000&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have 4 ethernet ports in the apartment wired up (one in each of the 3 bedrooms, and one in the living room), so since I’d only have 3 LAN ports on this router, I needed a small switch to wire up them all.  So I picked up tp-link’s 5-port &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tp-link.com/us/business-networking/easy-smart-switch/tl-sg105e/&quot;&gt;TL-SG105E&lt;/a&gt; as well for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00N0OHEMA&quot;&gt;$22.39 on Amazon&lt;/a&gt; which solves that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some relatively simple configuration, I now have the router configured to normally route me through the gigabit connection, but monitor that connection to make sure it says online.  If the connection is detected as going offline, the router will automatically switch everyone in the apartment over to the slower (but presumably still online) cable connection.  At what point it detects that the main connection is back online, it will automatically switch back to the faster connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve simulated these outages several different ways and the most I spend offline is about 20 seconds, which is very reasonable for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-functionality-of-the-tl-r605&quot;&gt;Other functionality of the TL-R605&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned before that the TL-R605 was surprisingly feature rich.  While the multi-WAN support was my primary draw to the device, I was pleasantly surprised to see a lot of other traditionally business related features are there as well, and I’ll make use of a lot of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vpn&quot;&gt;VPN&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TL-R605 supports up to 68 concurrent VPN connections, many of which can be LAN-to-LAN, allowing for seamless connection of networks in multiple locations into a single large network.  It supports 16 connections using &lt;a href=&quot;https://openvpn.net/&quot;&gt;OpenVPN&lt;/a&gt;, with an additional 16 connections using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Layer_2_Tunneling_Protocol&quot;&gt;L2TP&lt;/a&gt; and 16 connections using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Point-to-Point_Tunneling_Protocol&quot;&gt;PPTP&lt;/a&gt;.  On top of all that, an additional 20 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPsec&quot;&gt;IPsec&lt;/a&gt; connections in either Client-to-LAN or LAN-to-LAN modes are supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IPsec is particularly interesting as traditionally IPsec is expensive to license, and even expensive routers often don’t support all 4 of these protocols at the same time.  I will certainly be setting up both inbound and outbound VPN connections to give me flexibility, making external resources available to me, as well as giving me a way to connect home when I’m outside of the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vlan-and-vlan-routing&quot;&gt;VLAN and VLAN Routing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common feature on expensive business routers is the concept of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_LAN&quot;&gt;Virtual LAN&lt;/a&gt;, the idea of running multiple isolated network environments over the same physical network and handling each of them differently.  Individual clients can specify which VLAN they want to be a part of by specifying a number between 1 and 4094, and you can also configure specific ports on either the router OR smart network switches (like the previously mentioned TL-SG105E) to force users onto a specific VLAN automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having isolation can increase security as well as network throughput, especially when dealing with a broadcast situation.  Some devices send out messages to an entire network at once, meaning any time those devices are broadcasting, it impacts the bandwidth of all other devices on the network.  By isolating these devices onto a specific VLAN, I can ensure that broadcast messages from those devices only go to the other devices in the same VLAN, freeing up valuable bandwidth on other network ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different VLANs can also have their routing be different.  You can have a VLAN that doesn’t access the internet at all, you can have a VLAN that can access the internet and other devices on the network, you can have a VLAN that only can access the internet without giving them access to the rest of the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more exciting you can have different VLANs routed through the different WANs by default.  For example, I have a lot of IoT devices in my apartment, these need access to the internet but don’t need the high speeds that my computers do.  To free up a little internet bandwidth on my main internet connection I can configure the IoT devices to go out through the slower internet connection by default even if the main internet is online.  Doing so actually is better both for computers AND the IoT devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;guest-networks-with-captive-portal&quot;&gt;Guest Networks with Captive Portal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a wireless access point that supports VLANs for internal vs guest connections, I can also handle that through the main router.  This isn’t a particularly high priority for me right now as I have no guests coming by my home during the pandemic, but eventually I am likely to look into replacing my wifi with an access point that supports this, such as the companion devices from tp-link such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08PW34WPX/&quot;&gt;EAP660 HD&lt;/a&gt; which also supports the newer WiFi 6 standard.  When I do, this router supports setting up a captive portal where guests can’t simply connect to an open wifi, but have to authenticate using some means or another.  I can setup the captive portal to allow many different methods of authenticating, including using facebook login to authenticate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;staying-online&quot;&gt;Staying Online&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am extremely happy with this device and my now much more robust network setup at home.  There are still things I want to do to improve my network setup (starting with cleaning up the rats nest of wires that was left by the previous tenant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to setup a full internal server for my home, perhaps even a cluster I can run &lt;a href=&quot;https://kubernetes.io/&quot;&gt;K8s&lt;/a&gt; on and push an internal cluster of containers for development and management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am already running my own internal DNS server that doesn’t call up to my ISPs dns server within the home.  This is currently running on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi 4&lt;/a&gt; but I’d like to increase to a more powerful home server in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d also like to pick up a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uninterruptible_power_supply&quot;&gt;Uninterruptible Power Supply (UPS)&lt;/a&gt; for my network closet, so that a short power outage won’t result in all the devices having to reboot and spend the several minutes to boot up again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Tech" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Reviews" /><category term="Networking" /><category term="Routers" /><category term="TP-Link" /><category term="Internet" /><summary type="html">Working from home makes reliable internet essential, if the internet goes down for days I can't work, to combat this, I need to have another weapon at the ready.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Growing Behind the Stage</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/04/learning-behind-the-stage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Growing Behind the Stage" /><published>2021-03-04T19:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/04/learning-behind-the-stage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/04/learning-behind-the-stage/">&lt;p&gt;I love Live Theatre, I love attending as an audience member, I love acting (though I haven’t gotten to do that in a decade and a half), and I love working behind the scenes (mostly in Sound Design, but I’ve done a number of different jobs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years I’ve made an effort to try something new with most shows I do.  I either learn a new skill or try a new experiment.  With my latest show open, I thought I’d go over some of the new things I’ve learned or tried in the last few years of shows, as well as a peek at what i’ve done for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zoomtheater.com/index.php/shows/the-tempest&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Tempest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-theatrical-past&quot;&gt;My Theatrical past&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-college-years-2005-2006&quot;&gt;The College Years 2005-2006&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/mcm1940.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Musical Comedy Murders of 1940&quot; width=&quot;768&quot; height=&quot;1024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/mcm1940.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Musical Comedy Murders of 1940&quot; width=&quot;768&quot; height=&quot;1024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never finished college, but while I was there at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tccd.edu&quot;&gt;Tarrant County College&lt;/a&gt; in Arlington, TX I did get to participate in 3 productions.  In February of 2005, I &lt;a href=&quot;/2005/01/24/drama-king/&quot;&gt;acted in a production&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Musical_Comedy_Murders_of_1940&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Musical Comedy Murders of 1940&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as the character of Roger Hopewell.  I had long loved theatre before this, but after acting in that show, I was hooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later that spring I served as Light Board Operator for the school’s production of William Shakespeare’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Midsummer_Night%27s_Dream&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Midsummer Night’s Dream&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which I found every bit as enjoyable as acting.  This was in a way the beginning of my learning new tasks with shows as I did not have much prior experience with theatrical lighting (other than the simple light system at my church at the time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/rumors.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Rumors&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/rumors.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rumors&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following winter I acted in another production, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rumors_(play)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rumors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Neil Simon in the role of Ken Gorman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-lost-decade-2007-2017&quot;&gt;The lost decade 2007-2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I moved to California to work for Justia, I focused my energy on working for a while and did not get any opportunities to act in or crew any shows.  I did however get multiple opportunities to see theatrical productions, however.  I enjoyed seeing professional productions of &lt;em&gt;Wicked&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Promises, Promises&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spamalot&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/2012/10/13/newsies-on-broadway/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Newsies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying&lt;/em&gt;, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also saw a number of community theatre productions including: &lt;em&gt;A Funny Thing Happens on the Way to the Forum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Into the Woods&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;The Mystery of Edwin Drood&lt;/em&gt; (at my future community theatre home of Sunnyvale Community Players).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;returning-to-theatre-2017&quot;&gt;Returning to Theatre, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2017, after working with Justia for 10 full years, I decided the time was right to return to the theatre in some capacity.  I didn’t think I had the free time available to act again, but when I saw an email from SCP (I ended up on their mailing list after I attended &lt;em&gt;Drood&lt;/em&gt;) that they were looking for sound people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/drowsy.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Drowsy Chaperone&quot; width=&quot;3000&quot; height=&quot;1686&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/drowsy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Drowsy Chaperone&quot; width=&quot;3000&quot; height=&quot;1686&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having had some experience with sound from my time at &lt;em&gt;Eden Road&lt;/em&gt;, I reached out and came on as a sound board operator for SCP’s production of &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20170613202413/http://www.sunnyvaleplayers.org/the-drowsy-chaperone.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Drowsy Chaperone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  With this production just learning how live sound works in the 2010s was a learning curve for me.  The last sound-board I had used before then was an analog board, so just learning digital sound with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.midasconsoles.com/product.html?modelCode=P0B3I&quot;&gt;Midas M32&lt;/a&gt; was a learning curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the 2017 summer I got a chance to run sound for &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/07/10/next-normal-next-perfect/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Next to Normal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; up in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/fiddler.webp&quot; alt=&quot;SCP Fiddler on the Roof&quot; width=&quot;4048&quot; height=&quot;3036&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/fiddler.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SCP Fiddler on the Roof&quot; width=&quot;4048&quot; height=&quot;3036&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fall of 2017 I had one of the most pivotal events of my life when I worked on my second SCP production, &lt;em&gt;Fiddler on the Roof&lt;/em&gt;.  This show was so incredible that I am embarrassed for myself that I haven’t really written a full post about it before.  I will have to write up a full retrospective of that show in the future, but it changed my life in many ways.  The show was also big thanks to the incredible contribution of Eric Sun as our Fiddler.  The show was actually written up in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2018/01/01/a-tech-pioneers-final-unexpected-act&quot;&gt;The New Yorker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction-of-video-avenue-q&quot;&gt;Introduction of Video, &lt;em&gt;Avenue Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20170923135233/http://www.sunnyvaleplayers.org/avenue-q.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avenue Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I got my first experience with dealing with video effects in a show.  I was just an operator on the show, so I didn’t learn too much, but I did get to experiment with video from QLab for the first time in this show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-sound-design-2018&quot;&gt;Learning Sound Design, 2018&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;addams-family&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Addams Family&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/addams.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Addams Family&quot; width=&quot;2833&quot; height=&quot;1500&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/addams.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Addams Family&quot; width=&quot;2833&quot; height=&quot;1500&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Addams Family in early 2018 I got my first opportunity to design sound.  I co-designed sound with the great Dan Singletary and learned how to create my own sound effects, and learned a lot about balancing a band and equalization techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to overlapping shows, I went back to an operator for &lt;em&gt;La Cage aux Folles&lt;/em&gt; but I learned a lot in that show as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2018-2019&quot;&gt;2018-2019&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;producing-pins-and-jukebox&quot;&gt;Producing, Pins, and Jukebox&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;high-school-musical-jr-and-grease&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;High School Musical, JR&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Grease&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, my first experiences with producing probably should not have been 2 shows at the same time, but due to overlapping production schedules I was learning on my feet with producing 2 shows at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/pins.webp&quot; alt=&quot;SCP50 Pins&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/pins.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SCP50 Pins&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grease&lt;/em&gt; marked the first show in SCP’s 50th season, so to celebrate, I got my first experience with physical product design as I designed a run of collectable pins for the season.  The pins were popular and it gave me an opportunity to do some actual design.  With the help of my artistic brother, I designed a unique pin for each show in the 50th season, as well as a season pin that brought aspects of the 4 pins together into a single pin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grease&lt;/em&gt; also marked the beginning of my concept of wanting to “plus” my designs.  I learned how to have QLab actually control the sound board, and I used this skill to have the show’s pre-show music not come from a predefined playlist like usual.  Instead I used 2 tablets to create a jukebox, one in the lobby in a jukebox facadé, and one in the sound booth plugged into an input on the sound board.  With this I had a number of 50s era songs put up for selection in the jukebox and the audience got to choose the songs that would play both before the show and in intermission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it was set in the same general time-frame, I re-used this jukebox in &lt;em&gt;Bye, Bye, Birdie&lt;/em&gt; in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sound-design-programmed-tricks&quot;&gt;Sound Design Programmed Tricks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with &lt;em&gt;Bye, Bye, Birdie&lt;/em&gt; I started experimenting with programming more unique audio effects into the shows I did sound design for.  &lt;em&gt;Birdie&lt;/em&gt; has both &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diegetic_music&quot;&gt;diegetic&lt;/a&gt; and non-diegetic, in that some of the songs in the show are “performances” by Conrad Birdie and are thus “really” happening within the context of the show.  I decided a nice way to differentiate this is by having a different reverb on Birdie’s voice when the song was diegetic then when he was singing a song that was non-diegetic.  It was a simple effect, but it added a little something extra to a show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-overkill-jekyll-and-hyde&quot;&gt;Going overkill, &lt;em&gt;Jekyll and Hyde&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;Jekyll &amp;amp; Hyde&lt;/em&gt; I returned to the producer role, but I also sound designed again.  As a producer on this show, I spent some time learning photoshop and InDesign and created all of the marketing materials of the show myself.  I was very proud of my poster designs which was also used in the show’s program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my sound design of the show I continued with my trend of special audio effects by having a different equalization on Hyde’s voice than Jekyll’s.  This helped push the narrative that these characters were distinct as the quality of their voices were different.  I also played some with audio panning of vocals in this show.  In the pivotal “Confrontation” song I had Jekyll &amp;amp; Hyde’s voices coming from different sides of the stage, which was difficult considering both parts are sung by the same person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/D85_4702.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Magic Mirror&quot; width=&quot;3500&quot; height=&quot;2333&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/D85_4702.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Magic Mirror&quot; width=&quot;3500&quot; height=&quot;2333&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If producing and sound design weren’t enough, I also took on the task of doing a special visual effect for the show.  The director wanted a “magic mirror” effect in the show, so I learned video editing and how to use QLab to dynamically switch between a live camera feed and a pre-recorded video.  The effect was impressive, for most of the show this “mirror” actually “reflected” the environment around by showing a live camera feed, but at pivotal moments, Hyde or Jekyll would appear in the mirror to contrast the opposing character that was currently in control of Doctor Jekyll’s body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-magic-hourglass-freaky-friday&quot;&gt;The Magic Hourglass, &lt;em&gt;Freaky Friday&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/D85_6238.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Freaky Friday Hourglass&quot; width=&quot;2400&quot; height=&quot;2400&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/D85_6238.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Freaky Friday Hourglass&quot; width=&quot;2400&quot; height=&quot;2400&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Freaky Friday&lt;/em&gt;, the magical McGuffin that sets the story in motion is a magical hourglass.  The hourglass breaks immediately after its magic causes the body-swap to take place, and they spend the rest of the show trying to find another magic hourglass to switch them back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to take on a task of making this magic hourglass for the show.  In this I learned a bit of building physical props, including recycling items (coke bottles), a bit of wood-working, creating secret ways to break the device apart.  Most importantly I used this to get into Internet-of-Things devices by creating small wifi controlled light pods which could be put into compartments in the top and bottom of the hourglass.  With some python and third party tools I made it where the lights in the hourglass could be controlled by the theatre light-board so the lighting designer could include the glowing in his lighting design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pandemic&quot;&gt;The Pandemic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately 1 week after the show closed, the pandemic hit and we could no longer produce live theatre in front of audiences.  I spent the better part of the year not being involved in any theatre at all, but then one of my friends who I worked with at SCP contacted me about a show he was doing with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zoomtheatre.com&quot;&gt;Zoom Theatre&lt;/a&gt; over Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I had seen a number of zoom shot shows over the year of the pandemic, this was unique in that they invited the audience to actually join the zoom meeting and enable their microphones so that the actors can get real-time feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theatre-over-zoom-i-and-you&quot;&gt;Theatre over Zoom, &lt;em&gt;I and You&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My learning in &lt;em&gt;I and You&lt;/em&gt; was mostly about learning how theatre works over zoom.  Zoom Theatre is great in that rather than just having actors read over a zoom like a dramatic reading, they actually work to both exemplify the strengths of zoom (like the ability to switch cameras and switch backgrounds easily), and minimize the weaknesses to really make it feel like actors are together in the same room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how they actively slice up background images so that the different zoom windows of the individual actors line up.  They then work with duplicate props and careful choreography to do things like prop hand-offs, helping to sell the idea that people are actually together in the same room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live Theatre has always required suspension of disbelief, which takes on another meaning when acting over Zoom.  Since actors aren’t physically in the same space, you need to do everything you can to allow the audience to suspend their disbelief and actually believe that people are in the same space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;real-time-visual-effects-the-tempest&quot;&gt;Real-Time Visual Effects, &lt;em&gt;The Tempest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/tempest-1260x717.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Tempest&quot; width=&quot;1260&quot; height=&quot;717&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/tempest-1260x717.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Tempest&quot; width=&quot;1260&quot; height=&quot;717&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally after a very long post, I get to the show I’m currently working on.  &lt;em&gt;The Tempest&lt;/em&gt; is also being put on by Zoom Theatre and it is phenomenal.  For this show however I was tasked with creating some real-time visual effects using a combination of &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsproject.com/&quot;&gt;OBS Studio&lt;/a&gt; and, believe-it-or-not, Snapchat’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://snapcamera.snapchat.com/&quot;&gt;Snap Camera&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the filter creation tool &lt;a href=&quot;https://lensstudio.snapchat.com/&quot;&gt;Lens Studio&lt;/a&gt; (also by Snap), I created a number of unique snap filters which at key points in the show can be switched on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the show is over I’ll put up another post outlining exactly how I created the snap filters as well as the effects in OBS Studio that actually allow characters to break out of their zoom window in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see these effects in action, &lt;a href=&quot;https://zoomtheatre.com/index.php/shows/the-tempest&quot;&gt;come see &lt;em&gt;The Tempest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it is as close as you can get to live theatre while having everyone involved practicing social distancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part, you can see this phenomenal show, and my visual effects for FREE!.  The tickets cost you nothing, we have 4 performances remaining (as of the time of publication).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://us02web.zoom.us/webinar/register/WN_s0AKRLrZT9C3yik6ifmB9w&quot;&gt;&lt;time datetime=&quot;2021-03-04T19:00:00-08:00&quot;&gt;Thursday, March 4th, 2021, 7pm PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://us02web.zoom.us/webinar/register/WN_ZJtUql_JQ0STaTkjjSK8Ig&quot;&gt;&lt;time datetime=&quot;2021-03-05T19:00:00-08:00&quot;&gt;Friday, March 5th, 2021, 7pm PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://us02web.zoom.us/webinar/register/WN__-ZxjMspQ3CaNLuRSiqXag&quot;&gt;&lt;time datetime=&quot;2021-03-06T17:00:00-08:00&quot;&gt;Saturday, March 6th, 2021, 5pm PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://us02web.zoom.us/webinar/register/WN_rusyR1vJQ86l3MN_IFVbtQ&quot;&gt;&lt;time datetime=&quot;2021-03-07T14:00:00-08:00&quot;&gt;Sunday, March 7th, 2021, 2pm PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Theatre" /><category term="Learning" /><category term="Sound Design" /><category term="Visual Effects" /><category term="Photo Editing" /><summary type="html">With every show I work I try to learn at least one new skill, to bring one new thing to a production that I hadn't before.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">That Time I Made a Harpy</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/15/making-a-harpy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="That Time I Made a Harpy" /><published>2021-03-04T19:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/15/real-time-visual-effects</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2021/03/15/making-a-harpy/">&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/03/04/learning-behind-the-stage/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned that with each show I work on, I like to learn something new.  I teased that I had some very unique challenges on this latest show &lt;em&gt;The Tempest&lt;/em&gt;.  In particular I needed to create a number of real-time visual effects.  I used a variety of tools to accomplish this task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Tempest&lt;/em&gt; is a show that is known for involving quite a lot of spectacle and translating that spectacle to a real-time production over zoom was always going to be a challenge.  In this post I’ll break down a few of these effects including the tools I used to make them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-harpy&quot;&gt;The Harpy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Tempest&lt;/em&gt;, there is a scene where the spirit Ariel appears in the form of a harpy in order to frighten and shame the king and his party for what they did to Prospero in the past (&lt;em&gt;spoiler alert for a 410 year old play&lt;/em&gt;).  In the scenes immediately prior and following this, Ariel appears not as a harpy but as their normal spirit self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a stage this would require a costume quick-change into and out of a pretty significant costume that often needs the assistance of dressers to assist the actor.  With us all in quarantine, there was no dresser near the actor who played Ariel in order to allow for such an elaborate costume change.  The director (Pat Nims, the creator of &lt;a href=&quot;https://zoomtheatre.com&quot;&gt;Zoom Theatre&lt;/a&gt;) suggested that we could use &lt;a href=&quot;https://snapcamera.snapchat.com/&quot;&gt;Snap Camera&lt;/a&gt; (a desktop application by Snapchat that lets you use snapchat filters with your webcam) to essentially create a virtual costume for Ariel as a harpy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I couldn’t find a snapchat filter that would accomplish this task among the thousands of snapchat filters available.  When something doesn’t exist… make it yourself.  Snapchat also has an application called &lt;a href=&quot;https://lensstudio.snapchat.com/&quot;&gt;Lens Studio&lt;/a&gt; that allows you to create your own snapchat filters which can then be published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was difficult, as it involved mapping 2 dimensional images into a 3 dimensional AR mesh of the human face and shoulders, but the end result was fantastic.  In order to make the filter usable, I had to actually publish it to snapchat’s library of filters, which means if you would like, you can become a harpy either in snapchat on your phone or in lens studio yourself using the filter I made for this production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snapchat.com/unlock/?type=SNAPCODE&amp;amp;uuid=b221e35242564672a10561598efd1a1e&amp;amp;metadata=01&quot;&gt;&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/harpy-snapcode.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Become a Harpy&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;320&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/harpy-snapcode.png&quot; alt=&quot;Become a Harpy&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;320&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snap the snapcode above on your phone to use it on your phone, or copy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snapchat.com/unlock/?type=SNAPCODE&amp;amp;uuid=b221e35242564672a10561598efd1a1e&amp;amp;metadata=01&quot;&gt;this url&lt;/a&gt; and paste it into the search box in Snap Camera to use it on your computer webcam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flying-between-windows&quot;&gt;Flying Between Windows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom Theatre makes use of zoom’s gallery view and the feature of multi-spotlighting to arrange which user appears on which part of the screen.  We then use zoom’s background image feature to slice up a background image so that the various windows connect together to appear as one large image, helping to sell the idea that these actors are all together in the same space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a scene where 3 roman goddesses appear to bless the impending nuptuals of the romantic leads of the show.  The director wanted 2 of these goddesses to appear “in the sky” and then “descend” down to earth during the scene.  What he wanted is for these godddesses to appear in one part of the screen, and then move to another part of the screen (basically move between zoom windows)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accomplish this, we doubled up the computers at the 2 actors location.  They had 2 different computers connected to the same zoom call allowing us to pin the actor to essentially be in 2 places at once.  We then used &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsproject.com/&quot;&gt;OBS Studio&lt;/a&gt; to create a virtual webcam on both computers that would allow us to control the positioning of the camera in both spaces and animate the movement between them.  On one of the computers I had the actor appear at the top of the scene (camera on dead center), on the other the actor doesn’t appear (nothing but a green background which could then be chroma keyed out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then created a transition animation between 2 “scenes” (OBS Terminology) where on the top the camera image would be animated to descend out of the frame, and on the other the camera would descend into the frame.  With techs on both computers ready to hit the animation simultaneously, we were able to create an effective transition where the goddess Iris would descend from the sky on the top left of the overall image, and into the ground view on the bottom left.  A short while later, the goddess Juno would descend from the top right to the bottom right.  When timed correctly this effect worked very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the use of OBS, we did a similar effect earlier in the show where we had 2 cameras on 2 computers aimed low and high, so an actor laying down could stand up causing their torso to appear on the top row of windows and their legs to appear on the bottom row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effects were impressive and really helped build a virtual “stage” that the audience could suspend disbelief to feel like actors were really sharing the stage together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-goddesses-show-their-powers&quot;&gt;The Goddesses Show Their Powers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those same goddesses I mentioned earlier (along with a third goddess, Ceres) also needed another effect (a unique one for each of them) to help make them stand out in their big dance number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/goddesses.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Goddesses&quot; width=&quot;3140&quot; height=&quot;1804&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/goddesses.png&quot; alt=&quot;Become a Harpy&quot; width=&quot;3140&quot; height=&quot;1804&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these effects is unique and I accomplished them in different ways&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iris-goddess-of-the-rainbow&quot;&gt;Iris, Goddess of the Rainbow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both Greek and Roman mythology, Iris is the goddess of the rainbow.  For Iris I thought it might be interesting to create chromatic tinted ghost images that follow her movement.  To do this I used OBS again.  I duplicated the camera into 5 copies, with different filters on each virtual copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then layered these cameras (Each with chroma keying out) on top of each other to create the effect.  From top to bottom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top layer is just the camera itself, in full color, with the background chroma-keyed out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The next layer down is the same, except for 2 extra filters.  First I tinted the image red using color correction, and then made the image slightly transparent.  I then also put a small delay (100 miliseconds) so that when the top layer moves, the next layer would move a tenth of a second later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The next layer down is the same as above, except the delay is increased to 200 miliseconds and the color correction tints the image yellow instead of red.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The next layer down is the same as above, except the delay is increased to 300 miliseconds and the color correction tints the image blue instead of red or yellow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally the original camera image (without any corrections or even chroma keying) is placed on the background.  This allows the transparent colored layers to appear over the top of the background without issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ending effect makes it when Iris moves, there is a rainbow following her movement behind her.  I’m personally very happy with this effect as it is really unique.  It is possible to accomplish the same effect using snap filters, but it would require quite a bit of work and I was unable to get it to look as good in snap camera as I could in OBS in time for the show to open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;juno-queen-of-the-gods&quot;&gt;Juno, Queen of the Gods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Juno was difficult, she’s the queen of the Roman pantheon, but isn’t really associated with something that is an easy imagery like the rainbow for Iris.  I decided to simply give her an aura, specifically a purple aura, causing her to “glow” with purple regal light, kind of like the auras Disney used to represent most of the Greek pantheon in the animated &lt;em&gt;Hercules&lt;/em&gt; movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This purple aura I accomplished by creating yet another snap filter in Lens Studio where I used masking layers to create a glow, which I simply tinted purple.  This is a relatively simple filter, but I found it surprisingly difficult to get right where the aura would follow the actress without bleeding too much.  I spent a lot of time tweaking and improving the filter until I had the effect right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a screenshot of testing the filter on myself while I was working on it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/nick-glowing.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Nick is Glowing&quot; width=&quot;1418&quot; height=&quot;786&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/03/nick-glowing.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nick is Glowing&quot; width=&quot;1418&quot; height=&quot;785&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I had to publish this filter as well, if you are interested in turning yourself purple &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snapchat.com/unlock/?type=SNAPCODE&amp;amp;uuid=0628b20fcfed427a8a0f5fed6b87819c&amp;amp;metadata=01&quot;&gt;you can&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ceres-goddess-of-agriculture&quot;&gt;Ceres, Goddess of Agriculture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ceres is the Roman aspect of the Greek Goddess Demeter, the goddess of agriculture, grain crops, fertility and motherly relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a hard time coming up with an effect for this one, but in the end I happened across a snap filter that someone else created.  Someone who goes by Virtuose Reality created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snapchat.com/unlock/?type=SNAPCODE&amp;amp;uuid=34225a140f534044918282fa5a9445bb&amp;amp;metadata=01&quot;&gt;snap filter&lt;/a&gt; where after a few moments a crown made of vines grows around the head of the wearer, then flowers bloom, and finally a hummingbird starts flying around drinking from the flowers.  This a seriously impressive filter, that I can’t take ANY credit for.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snapchat.com/unlock/?type=SNAPCODE&amp;amp;uuid=34225a140f534044918282fa5a9445bb&amp;amp;metadata=01&quot;&gt;Try it out&lt;/a&gt;, it’s really cool, and worked fantastically for the Goddess of Agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-visual-effects&quot;&gt;Other Visual Effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other effects in the show, including some devil dogs which was created with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snapchat.com/unlock/?type=SNAPCODE&amp;amp;uuid=2eda6d9adcc3428a8bd5e9d0d75038f9&amp;amp;metadata=01&quot;&gt;another filter I found&lt;/a&gt; that puts a dog head shaped helmet on top of your head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We considered using a red eye effect on Caliban, but in the end we decided not to bother with it as it would make camera changes more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some other effects were accomplished by using video files that Pat created as the backgrounds, which I can’t take any credit for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sound-design&quot;&gt;Sound Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This show also had a ton of sound effects to work with, many of which required layering different sounds on top of each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I did in this show that I don’t often have to do is create background audio “loops.”  For those that don’t know creating an audio loop is a technique of making sure the end of the audio file matches up perfectly with the beginning of the audio file so that the sound could loop continuously without anybody noticing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pat wanted to make sure that the magic storm that shipwrecked people on Prospero’s island was always “present” which I accomplished by creating a number of long audio loops that could play in the background quietly without people noticing how much they were repeating.  A few well placed thunderclaps over the top of that audio loop helped also distract people from noticing the 10 minute audio loops as being loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zoom-on-remote-control&quot;&gt;Zoom on Remote Control&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally one more thing that Zoom Theatre did with this show that they had not previously done, is use a new custom zoom client by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.liminalet.com/&quot;&gt;Liminal Entertainment Technologies&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.liminalet.com/zoomosc&quot;&gt;ZoomOSC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Sound_Control&quot;&gt;Open Sound Control (OSC)&lt;/a&gt; is a text based network protocol designed back in 2002 to allow for remote control of synthesizers and other equipment during a show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ZoomOSC is a custom created zoom client that listens for these commands from a show controller, and both relays the commands through Zoom’s chat feature to copies of ZoomOSC running on other computers as well as doing a number of things in response to these commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took some trickery to get to work properly, but in the end this allowed &lt;a href=&quot;https://qlab.app/&quot;&gt;QLab&lt;/a&gt;, the software I’ve long used for cueing up sound and video effects in theatre, to control not only my own zoom client, but the zoom clients of the actors.  I could use it to spotlight different participants at different times so that whenever a scene is supposed to change, I could bring up the appropriate actors for each scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software is quite powerful, it could be used to command each person’s zoom client to change cameras and backgrounds automatically as well as controlling muting and unmuting of audio throughout the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it was the first time Zoom Theatre used this software for a show, we started simple, with just using the software to control spotlighting, relying on Zoom Theatre’s tried and true methods of having crew members remoting into actor computers to handle everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-a-show&quot;&gt;What a Show&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you managed to see &lt;em&gt;The Tempest&lt;/em&gt;, you know it was an impressive undertaking that you don’t normally see in live theatre productions done over zoom, and hopefully you now have an appreciation of the work that was put into the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above is just the things that I was involved with, but we also had a music director create original musical compositions for the show, a costumer costuming people without ever seeing them to take measurements, shipping clothes to the actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a props master sending props to the actors, in some cases sending duplicates of the same props to multiple actors so that they could “hand off” a prop between zoom windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we had someone create original hand-painted backgrounds for every location in the show.  All of this work by many people came together to create a unique show experience that was a true joy to be a part of.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Theatre" /><category term="Learning" /><category term="Visual Effects" /><category term="The Tempest" /><summary type="html">For the latest show I've worked on, I had an unusual new challenge, could I turn someone into a Harpy in real time? How about turning a woman into a rainbow?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Monitoring Weather Conditions With the Ambient Weather WS-2902C</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/10/26/weather-tracking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Monitoring Weather Conditions With the Ambient Weather WS-2902C" /><published>2020-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/10/26/weather-station-online</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/10/26/weather-tracking/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don’t normally put a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/code&gt; in my blog posts, but I do feel the need to preface the beginning of this post by saying, while Irvine, CA is currently under Evacuation Orders, the Evacuation Order does not include my part of Irvine, we are currently safe, though the air quality is a bit poor.  I’ll be sure to update social media if we end up being evacuated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve long been fascinated by personal weather stations, and long wanted one of my own so I can track weather conditions at my exact location.  The last couple of years I’ve been particularly interested in tracking the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_quality_index&quot;&gt;Air Quality Index (AQI)&lt;/a&gt; along with other weather data. The reason for this was the annual wildfires that impact the air quality in the SF bay area (and other areas of the west coast).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, on a day the AQI in Sunnyvale was particularly bad (everything outside was tinted orange), I went ahead and purchased the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ambientweather.com/amws2902.html&quot;&gt;WS-2902C&lt;/a&gt; along with the optional addon units for measuring the PM2.5 Air Quality (one of the main factors that the AQI is calculated from) both inside and outside my apartment.  I went with the Ambient Weather unit for a number of reasons.  Of course having those Air Quality sensors were a big part of it, but I also was interested in being able to track weather online.  The Ambient Weather unit had the extra interesting improvements of integration with both IFTTT and Google Assistant, which fits into my smarthome setup quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time my unit arrived however the air quality was marginally better, and more importantly it was looking more and more likely that I was going to end up moving out of the bay area (&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/10/04/the-next-adventure/&quot;&gt;I did&lt;/a&gt;) so I didn’t set it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been in Irvine an entire month yet (heck I haven’t even reached 2 weeks yet) and now there are evacuations in this very city because of wildfires down here.  At the moment my new home (shown below as the blue dot) is not yet under evacuation orders (or an evacuation warning), but the smoke is in the air and the air quality is once again bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/fire-evacuations.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Map of Fire Evacuations in Irvine&quot; width=&quot;1355&quot; height=&quot;1252&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/fire-evacuations.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of Fire Evacuations in Irvine&quot; width=&quot;1355&quot; height=&quot;1252&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the air quality was bad again, the time was right to finally crack open the box and setup our new weather station.  While it looked complicated, assembly was fairly simple and I now have a fully functional internet connected weather station on my patio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-unit-and-my-setup&quot;&gt;The Unit and my Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the patio I have the Osprey Sensor array which includes a weather vane, speed cups, an Ambient/UV Light sensor, a Thermo-Hygrometer, and a rain gauge.  The unit is primarily powered by a solar panel on the top of the unit, with 2 AA batteries to provide backup power if not enough solar energy is collected in a given day.  The unit transmits via RF (at 915 MHz) to a console located inside the apartment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/PXL_20201027_064916207.NIGHT.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Weather Unit on my patio, yes there is construction outside, great view&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/PXL_20201027_064916207.NIGHT.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Weather Unit on my patio, yes there is construction outside, great view&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also on the patio is a separate solar powered unit which is the Outdoor version of the PM2.5 Particulate Monitor, which also communicates with the console inside via 915 MHz RF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/PXL_20201027_064931760.NIGHT.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Air Quality Sensor PM 2.5&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/PXL_20201027_064931760.NIGHT.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Air Quality Sensor PM 2.5&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the apartment is the centralized console.  The console contains an LED display unit.  Note when I say it is an LED, it is not a video screen.  The individual LEDs light up like a traditional LCD calculator (but lit) and each LED can only light a particular area of the display.  On the display are readouts for Wind Speed and Direction, Rainfall, Outdoor Temperature and Humidity, Time and Date, Moon Phase, Barometric Pressure, a Weather Forecaast, Solar Radiation, and the UV Index.  There is also a display for the Indoor temperature and Humidity which comes from another Thermo-Hygrometer sensor located in the console itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/PXL_20201027_065019498.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Main Console Display&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/PXL_20201027_065019498.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Main Console Display&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the 915 MHz RF receiver that receives communications from the other devices, this also contains a 2.4 GHz WiFi radio inside which is used to connect to your home WiFi connection for transmitting the data to the internet.  You’ll note I did not mention anything on the display that mentioned displaying the PM2.5 Particulate Monitor data, this data is only available on the internet dashboards and mobile app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/Screenshot_20201027-001612.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Viewing Air Quality on the Mobile App&quot; width=&quot;1080&quot; height=&quot;2160&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/Screenshot_20201027-001612.png&quot; alt=&quot;Viewing Air Quality on the Mobile App&quot; width=&quot;1080&quot; height=&quot;2160&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit can also receive from a second PM2.5 Particulate Monitor unit, which instead of being powered by solar is powered by a USB charger.  This is for monitoring the air quality inside the apartment, we placed this unit in our bedroom to get an indication of what the air quality is where Barbara will be spending most of her time.  The console can also receive from (and upload) data from up to 8 additional Thermo-Hygrometers.  We placed one of these in our bedroom to sense the temperature and humidity in our room, as well as another one in Joey’s (Barbara’s Brother) room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to purchase a 3rd to put into Dorothy’s (Barbara’s Mom) room to finish out the sensing in the apartment, but as I mentioned we purchased this in our old home where we only had 2 bedrooms so we only purchased 2 of them.  We’ll pick up an additional 1 (or possibly a few) to monitor other rooms. It would be interesting to monitor temperature and humidity in the bathrooms as I’m sure the humidity spikes whenever someone takes a shower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With everything setup, I can now access my data in a variety of places.  The unit’s native home is &lt;a href=&quot;https://ambientweather.net/dashboard/435a5c93160dc349b6a8f4b1cc27f054&quot;&gt;Ambient Weather’s own weather data service&lt;/a&gt; which works very well, but you can also set the unit up to upload directly to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wunderground.com/dashboard/pws/KCAIRVIN182&quot;&gt;Weather Underground&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.weathercloud.net/d2434962961#profile&quot;&gt;Weathercloud&lt;/a&gt;.  You aren’t limited to one of these services either, those links are links to the public versions of the weather data from my weather station on all 3 services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/dashboard.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Web Based Dashboard&quot; width=&quot;1727&quot; height=&quot;1444&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/weather/dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Web Based Dashboard&quot; width=&quot;1727&quot; height=&quot;1444&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Ambient Weather you can also integrate with a number of other 3rd party services.  The first is PWS Weather which doesn’t have as nice of an interface as any of the direct services, but what is nice is the ability to easily download a CSV log of the data, there’s no public view of this one that I can find so no link here.  If you don’t want to have your unit upload to Weather Underground directly, you can also just upload to Ambient Weather and have them integrate with Weather Underground from their service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more exciting integrations from Ambient Weather’s service is that it can integrate with Alexa, Google Assistant, and IFTTT.  I will surely be setting up some interesting integrations from IFTTT to automate things based on my weather data (for example flashing my smart lights red if the air quality gets particularly bad).  I could eventually do some automation with other pieces of equipment, for example I can turn on a humidifier if the humidity drops too low (or a dehumidifier if it gets too high), or an air filter whenever the air quality reaches certain thresholds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for Google Assistant, at this point the integration is a little limited, but it is nice to be able to ask a Google Home for one or more of the pieces of live weather data from my weather station.  I hope this integration will become more robust over time as I’d love to be able to replace standard internet data with my localized data, or integrate this data in routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’ll wrap this post by saying, if you are in an area that is being ravaged by wildfire, my thoughts and prayers are with you and your families.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Life" /><category term="Moving" /><category term="Weather" /><category term="Fire" /><summary type="html">As some people in my city are being evacuated due to encroaching fires, I finally setup my weather station to track the weather and air quality.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rolling up a New Character</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/10/04/the-next-adventure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rolling up a New Character" /><published>2020-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/10/04/the-next-adventure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/10/04/the-next-adventure/">&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, I’ve gotten into playing a lot of &lt;abbr title=&quot;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons&quot;&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt;. When a new campaign begins, it is fun to play a new character, to roll the stats of that character and start building his backstory, creating the new aspects of the character that make him unique, and then venturing out with a new group of friends to create a new story together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In real life we don’t start over so completely. And yet when you do make a major change, it can often feel like rolling up a new character to take on the next great adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly 14 years ago, my wife and I packed up a minivan and left Texas behind to move to Silicon Valley, California to start a new adventure. Here we were, knowing almost no one and starting life in a new home working at a new company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly a decade and a half later we have quite a life here, we have several different circles of friends, between coworkers and colleagues I’ve met through Justia, tech friends we met through tech conferences, and theater friends we met through Sunnyvale Community Players. I’ve traveled around the country going to legal tech conferences with Justia, and on the way I’ve gotten to see shows on Broadway and sporting events around the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten to dust off my sound operator skills running sound for a variety of theater productions, and I’ve grown those skills into sound design having designed sound for roughly half a dozen shows. More recently I’ve branched into special effects by creating a raspberry pi based solution for doing portable lighting effects on the stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life has been an adventure, and my little adventuring party has grown along the way. There are many I’d consider close friends here, and I’m glad to be with all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In D&amp;amp;D one of the most exciting parts of a campaign is when your party establishes a headquarters, a home base that they customize just for their party and offers respite from the rigors of adventuring life. Early on, adventurers are nomadic and spend little or no time at “home,” but later in the campaign, they need that home base in order to prepare for the challenges that lie ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, we all have faced challenges beyond anything that has happened in our lifetimes. The global pandemic has decimated the economy and killed hundreds of thousands of people. For those of us that haven’t gotten sick, we’ve had to adapt to a new way of life where we have to keep our distance from each other and do everything we can to protect ourselves and others (&lt;em&gt;I shouldn’t have to say this, but come on everyone, just wear a mask&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big part of that has been staying home a lot more. We’ve all been forced to retreat to our homes, to our home bases, our headquarters, to stave off the invading hoard of the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many people I know, this has been annoying, but overall livable, but for others, such as Barbara and I, having to spend all our time at our home base in close quarters has simply driven home just how inadequate of a base our home is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 14 years working at Justia, I’m paid very well compared to the average American, but as someone living in the heart of Silicon Valley I’ve had to pay a princely sum every month in order to pay for my pauper dwelling. In D&amp;amp;D “lifestyle” terms, my Level 14 Code Wizard has his spending setting set to “Aristocratic (10GP),” but lives in accommodations that would be classified as “Modest (1GP)” at best, or perhaps even “Poor (2SP).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be more specific, for the past year I’ve paid over $4,000 a month for a tiny 2 bedroom apartment.  And with 4 adults currently living in that 2 bedroom apartment, and those 4 adults spending every waking moment there except for occasional trips to a grocery store, this is not the type of home base I should have at this point in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is nothing against Justia or even against Silicon Valley, people choose to live here for a reason, and for a while it was exciting living the Silicon Valley life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pandemic has made me realize, however, that this is not the type of lifestyle I want to live long term. This is not the type of character I want to play indefinitely. I’d like to be able to live in a house, with a kitchen large enough to make gourmet meals, and perhaps a nice grill in the back yard. I’d love to have a garage I can setup a workshop in, to take on new, more creative projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly of all I’d like to have a separate workspace from my life space. I’d like to have an office where I can work separate from where I go to relax, where I can close myself off to be able to focus on work when I’m working, and close myself away from it when I’m playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, I’d also love it if I had a place where I could play D&amp;amp;D with friends around a table, the way the game was designed to be played (perhaps on a custom gaming table built in that workshop).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I don’t see my current adventure leading to that life, as Silicon Valley will always be so expensive to live that I won’t be able to afford to establish that headquarters for my adventuring party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, the time has come to roll a new character, to take on a new adventuring party and start off on a new adventure with that life as the endgame. I’m happy to announce that I’ve now taken a new position as Senior Software Engineer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.Ezoic.com&quot;&gt;Ezoic, Inc&lt;/a&gt; in Carlsbad, CA, and Barbara and I (along with her mother and brother who live with us), will be moving to southern California before the end of this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last day with Justia will be October 15th, and my first official (but remote) day with Ezoic will be October 19th, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve found a place to live, a temporary headquarters to start our journey down there in. For roughly $500/month less than I’ve been paying for this 2 bedroom apartment here, we’ve found a 3 bedroom apartment down there with more than twice the square footage, giving us all a lot more breathing room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t the house with a yard and a garage I can use as a workshop yet, but in order to save money on breaking my lease early, I had to choose an apartment owned by the same organization that owns my current apartment complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/new-kitchen.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Check out that Kitchen!&quot; width=&quot;6342&quot; height=&quot;2406&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2020/10/new-kitchen.png&quot; alt=&quot;Check out that Kitchen!&quot; width=&quot;6342&quot; height=&quot;2406&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it doesn’t give me my dream home right away, it is a lot more space and should be a lot more comfortable. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://my.matterport.com/show/?m=LBF9qr6AHpw&amp;amp;sr=-2.55,.79&amp;amp;ss=3&quot;&gt;kitchen is also glorious&lt;/a&gt; being much larger than my current kitchen and containing advantages over my current kitchen, including a gas stove. My plan is to move again later, to a house that matches my desired criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is bittersweet to set off of this new adventure. I will miss my friends here in the bay area, and I’ll miss Justia. I’ve loved working at Justia and have been very proud of the free legal information projects I’ve been a part of there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, however, I’m very excited about what comes next. It is exciting to start a new campaign, to find new challenges.  I’m excited to see what projects I’ll get to work on at Ezoic, and I’m very excited to start anew in a new area (well mostly new, I spent the first 10 years of my life in Southern California, and Barbara and I have visited Disneyland in Southern California, between 1 and 4 times a year for the last decade).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your party sets out southward towards a new city, and a new home, with new foes to defeat, new challenges to undertake, and a new adventure around every corner.  Your party stumbles across something exciting along the way, Roll for Initiative.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Life" /><category term="Moving" /><category term="Justia" /><category term="Ezoic" /><category term="Dungeons and Dragons" /><summary type="html">After 14 years in Silicon Valley, I'm packing up and moving to southern California, to take on new challenges.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to the new NickMoline.com</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/30/welcome-to-nickmoline.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to the new NickMoline.com" /><published>2020-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/30/welcome-to-nickmolinecom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/30/welcome-to-nickmoline.com/">&lt;p&gt;For several years, I’ve had 2 separate personal sites, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nickmoline.com&quot;&gt;NickMoline.com&lt;/a&gt;, which for many years was a single page portfolio page which contained nothing but a short bio of me, links to various social media profiles of mine, and a link to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nick.pro&quot;&gt;nick.pro&lt;/a&gt; which was my blog.  The portfolio page was a simple responsive HTML page (you can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nickmoline.com/nickmolinecom.html&quot;&gt;an archive of this page here&lt;/a&gt;), while the blog was running on WordPress and contained my musings on a variety of topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time though, both of these sites languished.  I posted to nick.pro only about once per year (&lt;em&gt;I missed 2018 entirely, with only a single post in 2019&lt;/em&gt;), and nickmoline.com I ignored so long I didn’t even realize it had been down for a long time until @emil10001 pointed out that my portfolio page was completely down.  Upon investigation, I noticed that it had actually been down for at least a year, and the last commit to the repo was &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nickmoline/nickmoline.github.io/commit/c0234b8c9205ada794d70e1a043a40cb16644533&quot;&gt;on September 1, 2016&lt;/a&gt; and consisted of only the &lt;a href=&quot;https://keybase.io/nickmoline&quot;&gt;Keybase&lt;/a&gt; verification file for the domain.  The last substantial content commits to the page was &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nickmoline/nickmoline.github.io/commit/ef5ad46df31bece8aad76f6bbae4e890cdb86d64&quot;&gt;in January, 2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;migration&quot;&gt;Migration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided the time had come to give the sites a drastic overhaul, and I decided that there really isn’t much reason for 2 separate sites anymore.  I decided to centralize the sites on the domain that matches my full name domain &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nickmoline.com/&quot;&gt;NickMoline.com&lt;/a&gt;.  I also decided that as much as I love WordPress, I don’t really need WordPress for my personal site.  As a coder, I’m actually more comfortable working in an IDE than a CMS.  As such I made the decision to &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/20/migrating-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;migrate my blog from WordPress to Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While an excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/plugins/jekyll-exporter/&quot;&gt;wordpress plugin&lt;/a&gt; to export posts into Jekyll compatible markdown files complete with front-matter exists, I wanted to take this opportunity to make my site 100% &lt;a href=&quot;https://amp.dev/&quot;&gt;AMP Only&lt;/a&gt; which meant either scripting a change between tags blocked by AMP, or going through the posts one by one and cleaning up the markup to make sure it is compatible with AMP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amp-only&quot;&gt;&lt;abbr title=&quot;Accelerated Mobile Pages&quot;&gt;AMP&lt;/abbr&gt; Only&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those readers who do not know, AMP is an HTML5 framework that &lt;a href=&quot;https://amp.dev/about/how-amp-works/&quot;&gt;puts limits&lt;/a&gt; on which tags are allowed and how dynamic scripts are executed.  The reason for this is speed, by following these limits &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/amp&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.bing.com/Webmaster-Blog/September-2018/Introducing-Bing-AMP-viewer-and-Bing-AMP-cache&quot;&gt;Bing&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.cloudflare.com/accelerated-mobile/&quot;&gt;others&lt;/a&gt; are able to cache the content of the pages in such a way that they can display the AMP content nearly instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote articles on Justia’s Legal Marketing &amp;amp; Technology Blog in &lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2017/02/02/amp-your-law-firm-mobile-site/&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2018/02/09/amp-update-get-even-amped-2018/&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt; in addition to a number of blog posts based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/tag/amp-project/&quot;&gt;events&lt;/a&gt; related to AMP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve long been a fan and champion of the AMP Project and feel it is an important step forward in cleaning up the web after decades of plugins, javascript libraries, extensive backend processing, and larger and larger static resources have resulted in a web that often doesn’t meet the performance demands of those who are using it. Google is well aware of this, as I posted on Justia’s blog in &lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2017/07/05/page-speed-tips-and-tools/&quot;&gt;July of 2017&lt;/a&gt; and have long been doing everything they can to make the web perform faster.  AMP is part of this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is possible (and in fact normal) to make AMP Equivalent versions of existing non-AMP pages for the sake of having the performance of AMP while not sacrificing the interactivity of non-AMP pages, I have long believed it is just as possible to have all of that same interactivity without sacrificing AMP, and as such I made the decision to go AMP only with my site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see evidence of this interactivity throughout this site, from things as simple as &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/05/30/google-io-2019-io19/&quot;&gt;embedded youtube videos&lt;/a&gt;, to more complex things such as &lt;a href=&quot;/2008/08/19/hours-away-from-vacation/&quot;&gt;photo gallery sliders with lightbox popups&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/2003/09/05/internet-fads/&quot;&gt;hovering videos that keep playing after you scroll away&lt;/a&gt;, all without compromising AMP’s various benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example on pages with lots of images or embeds such as my post about &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/05/30/google-io-2019-io19/&quot;&gt;Google I/O 2019&lt;/a&gt;, the embeds are only loaded as you scroll down the page, allowing what would normally stall rendering to be deferred until you scroll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In time I plan to add even more interactivity into this site by implementing &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.dev/progressive-web-apps/&quot;&gt;Progressive Web Apps&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;https://amp.dev/documentation/components/amp-install-serviceworker/&quot;&gt;amp-install-serviceworker&lt;/a&gt; to enable PWA functionality in my AMP page.  &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;amp-install-serviceworker&lt;/code&gt; allows AMP developers to implement the more dynamic functions that typically require extensive javascript libraries without compromising AMP’s requirements by installing it in the background after the content of the page has loaded.  Future loads of the site after that point will be even faster as the service worker will initiate right away and render the more dynamic content immediately upon page load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;image-optimization-and-webp&quot;&gt;Image optimization and WebP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another improvement I went through when I setup this new version of my site was optimizing every single image on the site.  I passed all of the JPEG, PNG and GIF images on the site through optimizers such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://imageoptim.com/&quot;&gt;ImageOptim&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://pngmini.com/&quot;&gt;ImageAlpha&lt;/a&gt; in order to make the images as small as possible without a noticeable decrease in image quality.  To make this process as efficient as possible I used the great &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/imageoptim-cli&quot;&gt;imageoptim-cli&lt;/a&gt; command line tool written in Node to enable me to automate the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to optimizing the PNG, JPEG, and GIF images as much as possible, I also used the open source &lt;a href=&quot;http://abic.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;Advanced Batch Image Converter&lt;/a&gt; application to create WebP versions of most of the images.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/speed/webp&quot;&gt;WebP&lt;/a&gt; is a relatively new image format created by Google along with it’s big brother &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmproject.org/&quot;&gt;WebM&lt;/a&gt; which is a video format.  Both formats were designed to make images and videos (respectively) load much quicker without sacrificing quality.  WebP supports alpha transparency like PNGs and full photo quality like JPEG while producing images that are on average 25-35% smaller than JPEG.  WebP even sorts &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq#why_should_i_use_animated_webp&quot;&gt;animations&lt;/a&gt; like the older more limited GIF format, allowing for far more robust image formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just about the only downside to WebP is that there are still a few holdouts as far as &lt;a href=&quot;https://caniuse.com/#feat=webp&quot;&gt;browser support&lt;/a&gt; when it comes to the format.  Safari (including iOS Safari) does not currently support WebP, however Apple has just announced that WebP image support is coming in the upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macrumors.com/2020/06/22/webp-safari-14/&quot;&gt;Safari 14&lt;/a&gt; which will ship with iOS 14 and macOS 11 Big Sur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Microsoft’s Internet Explorer does not support WebP (and won’t), Internet Explorer has been discontinued and  Microsoft’s own apps will stop supporting the browser starting with Microsoft Teams removing support on November 30th, 2020 and all Microsoft 365 apps &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/microsoft-365-blog/microsoft-365-apps-say-farewell-to-internet-explorer-11-and/ba-p/1591666&quot;&gt;removing support by August 17, 2021&lt;/a&gt;.  The newer Edge browser which replaces Internet Explorer &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.windows.com/msedgedev/2018/10/04/edgehtml-18-october-2018-update/&quot;&gt;added support for WebP in Edge version 18&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mozilla Firefox &lt;a href=&quot;https://hacks.mozilla.org/2019/01/firefox-65-webp-flexbox-inspector-new-tooling/#:~:text=Media%3A%20Support%20for%20WebP%20and,with%20the%20same%20image%20quality.&quot;&gt;added support for WebP in version 65&lt;/a&gt; released in January, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Apple’s Safari 14 achieves widespread adoption, we can comfortably say that WebP support has near universal support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to make sure that browsers that don’t yet support WebP, I made sure to implement the &lt;a href=&quot;https://amp.dev/documentation/guides-and-tutorials/develop/style_and_layout/placeholders/&quot;&gt;fallback&lt;/a&gt; protocol in the amp-img spec to ensure that browsers that don’t yet support WebP will be served the JPEG or PNG equivalent format instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;amp-img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;[webpurl]&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;width=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;x&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;height=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;y&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;responsive&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;lightbox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;amp-img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;fallback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;[jpegurl]&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;width=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;x&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;height=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;y&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;responsive&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;lightbox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/amp-img&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/amp-img&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ensures that browsers that do support WebP will be served the lighter faster image format, while browsers that don’t yet support it will still be able to work by being served a still optimized as much as possible JPEG or PNG version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cleaning-up-content&quot;&gt;Cleaning Up Content&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I went through every post by hand, I spent time cleaning up old pages that were originally marked up in XHTML or even &lt;a href=&quot;/2004/08/17/archive-tweaks/&quot;&gt;HTML4&lt;/a&gt;.  Some particularly bad posts include a &lt;a href=&quot;/2006/05/30/personality-test/&quot;&gt;personality test&lt;/a&gt; I took back in 2006 which had multiple embedded tables and had Gauges made by repeating pipe symbols (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;) to varying widths.  Without modifying the content of these posts, I took the liberty of redoing their markup using HTML 5 techniques including the same &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;progress&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag that I was using for the tracking gauge I had put up for tracking migration of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have corrected numerous spelling errors and other grammatical mistakes that I found highly embarrassing, again without altering the meaning or content of the posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous posts I found embarrassing, but rather than erase the past, I found it important to keep embarrassing content intact, only correcting spelling and grammar errors where necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tracking-migration&quot;&gt;Tracking Migration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing this migration slowly over the last 2 weeks.  Rather than wait for it to be complete, I put it up on nickmoline.com while leaving nick.pro operational, and put a status gauge on the home page indicating how much of the site had been migrated.  To prevent having to change this over and over manually, I did some simple trickery using Jekyll collections to &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/21/automating-progress-bar-in-jekyll/&quot;&gt;automate the gauge during Jekyll Builds&lt;/a&gt;.  Be sure to check out &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/21/automating-progress-bar-in-jekyll/&quot;&gt;the post&lt;/a&gt; for more on how I did this as well as to see what the gauge displayed over that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;progress max=&quot;212&quot; value=&quot;212.0&quot; title=&quot;100.0% migrated&quot;&gt;&lt;/progress&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Migrated &lt;strong&gt;212&lt;/strong&gt; out of &lt;strong&gt;212&lt;/strong&gt; posts migrated (&lt;strong&gt;100.0%&lt;/strong&gt;).  &lt;strong&gt;0&lt;/strong&gt; posts remaining to migrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;much-to-do&quot;&gt;Much to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have much to do.  I’ve been debating on if I want to add retroactive posts or not to link to content that I never posted on my blog but did post in other places such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/author/nickmoline/&quot;&gt;Justia’s Blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hp-lexicon.org/author/nickmoline/&quot;&gt;The Harry Potter Lexicon&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://sunnyvaleplayers.org/author/nickmoline/&quot;&gt;Sunnyvale Community Players&lt;/a&gt; but never bothered to post about on my own blog.  As well as events that had a huge impact on my life but I never posted about such as the various plays I have worked on or some of the conferences I’ve attended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment I’m leaning towards writing those retroactive posts, or at least some of them, but I haven’t done so yet.  And of course I intend on publishing lots of posts here in the future, especially on some of my more nerdy projects that I’ve been working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to spend some more time better organizing the &lt;a href=&quot;/categories/&quot;&gt;Categories&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/tags/&quot;&gt;Tags&lt;/a&gt; a bit as there are more categories than I’d like and there are places where there are multiple tags with the same meaning but without the same posts.  These tasks will come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the mean time &lt;strong&gt;Welcome to NickMoline.com&lt;/strong&gt;, I’m very glad to have you here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Web" /><category term="Writing" /><category term="Blogging" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="Coding" /><summary type="html">After several years of being separate, I've merged my personal sites of NickMoline.com and Nick.pro into a single site, and given it a pretty substantial overhaul at the same time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automating the site migration progress bar in Jekyll</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/21/automating-progress-bar-in-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automating the site migration progress bar in Jekyll" /><published>2020-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/21/automating-progress-bar-in-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/21/automating-progress-bar-in-jekyll/">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned yesterday &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/20/migrating-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;I’m moving posts over to Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; from my WordPress blog.  To get started, I used a wordpress plugin called simply &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/plugins/jekyll-exporter/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Exporter&lt;/a&gt; to export all of my posts and pages into markdown files.  This worked pretty well, but since I want my site to be 100% &lt;a href=&quot;https://amp.dev&quot;&gt;AMP&lt;/a&gt; Only, I decided that rather than just publishing them all I should make sure that none of the old markup (much of which has been migrated between 3 different platforms) ends up causing pages not to validate in the AMP Validator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided not to wait till I had converted all 212 pages to go live at nickmoline.com, but in the vein of old Under Construction pages of the 90s I decided it would be neat to display a progress bar on how much of the backlog I’ve worked my way through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;progress max=&quot;212&quot; value=&quot;212.0&quot; title=&quot;100.0% migrated&quot;&gt;&lt;/progress&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Migrated &lt;strong&gt;212&lt;/strong&gt; out of &lt;strong&gt;212&lt;/strong&gt; posts migrated (&lt;strong&gt;100.0%&lt;/strong&gt;).  &lt;strong&gt;0&lt;/strong&gt; posts remaining to migrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s cool about this bar (which is shows up not only here, but also on the home page and in the previous blog post) is that it is being generated entirely dynamically from my jekyll repo.  I thought it would be interesting to explain how I got my repo to generate this dynamically in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;determining-what-is-done&quot;&gt;Determining what is done&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jekyll has a global array called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site.posts&lt;/code&gt; which contains everything necessary to loop through all of the posts on the site.  In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://shopify.github.io/liquid/&quot;&gt;Liquid Template Language&lt;/a&gt; (the templating engine &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/liquid/&quot;&gt;Jekyll uses&lt;/a&gt;), you can use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.size&lt;/code&gt; to determine how many elements are in an array, including this list of posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way I’m able to determine how many posts have been written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;determining-what-is-not-done&quot;&gt;Determining what is not done&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Live posts in Jekyll are stored in a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; folder.  There is also a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_drafts&lt;/code&gt; folder which contains post drafts that you haven’t finished yet, but there’s a difference between drafts and what I’m doing here.  As such my first goal was to create a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/collections/&quot;&gt;Collection&lt;/a&gt; of the posts that have not been migrated yet.  I moved all of the posts that I had not yet checked for formatting and placed them in a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_pending&lt;/code&gt; folder, i then configured the collection by adding to my collections array in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-yml highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;collections&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This now creates a new collection named &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/code&gt; which works much the same as the built in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/code&gt;.  The list of pending posts are available in a separate array &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site.pending&lt;/code&gt; which I similarly can use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site.pending.size&lt;/code&gt; to get a count of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calculating-percentage&quot;&gt;Calculating Percentage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can now add the two values together to get a total count of posts both pending and live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-liquid highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;assign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;site&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;site&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;times&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;1.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math in Liquid is done with filters, so I take &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site.posts.size&lt;/code&gt; and I add with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;| plus:&lt;/code&gt; the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site.pending.size&lt;/code&gt; to get a total count.  You’ll notice I then multiply this by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1.0&lt;/code&gt;.  The reason I do this is to make sure the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/code&gt; variable is a floating point number, rather than an integer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the percentage, I can then divide &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site.posts.size&lt;/code&gt; by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-liquid highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;assign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;migration_percentage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;site&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;divided_by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;times&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;round&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For presentation’s sake I’m then multiplying by 100 and then rounding to 2 significant digits.  At this point I have all of the numbers I need.  I know how many published posts there are (currently &lt;strong&gt;212&lt;/strong&gt;), how many posts are pending migration (&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;), how many posts there are total (&lt;strong&gt;212&lt;/strong&gt;), and what percentage of the total posts are done (&lt;strong&gt;100.0%&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rendering-the-progress-bar&quot;&gt;Rendering the progress bar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The progress bar itself I’m rendering using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/html5-author/the-progress-element.html&quot;&gt;HTML5 tag progress element&lt;/a&gt; which is specifically designed for rendering this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-liquid highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;progress 
    max=&quot;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;floor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&quot; 
    value=&quot;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;site&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&quot; 
    title=&quot;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;migration_percentage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;% migrated&quot;
    &amp;gt;&amp;lt;/progress&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have set &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;max&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;100&lt;/code&gt; and used the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;migration_percentage&lt;/code&gt; as the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;value&lt;/code&gt;, but I thought using the actual values would make for a more accurate status bar as it would be calculated with a higher precision than I want to display.  I then set a title attribute so that when you hover over the progress bar you see the percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For styling the progress bar, I followed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://css-tricks.com/html5-progress-element/&quot;&gt;fantastic guide posted at css-tricks&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://pankajparashar.com/&quot;&gt;Panjak Parashar&lt;/a&gt; and then tweaked things a bit to my personal liking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that I can easily include this in multiple places, I stored all of this in an include file named migration-progress.html so that I could include it in multiple places (such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nickmoline.com&quot;&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/20/migrating-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;my previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;) and future tweaks could be shown in multiple places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;putting-it-all-together&quot;&gt;Putting it all together&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;amp-gist data-gistid=&quot;2744c66ccd46224b7c6e3a8196d73a30&quot; layout=&quot;fixed-height&quot; height=&quot;225&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-gist&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dealing-with-future-posts&quot;&gt;Dealing with future posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point some of you may have noticed a flaw in the above that this post actually exacerbates, it counts new posts as migrated posts.  The more I blog before the files are published, the more the numbers will be incorrect.  To solve this, when I finished I simply replaced the calculation making the total a fixed number (212) and calculating the number published as the total minus what is left in the pending folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the final modified version to take this into consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-liquid highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;assign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;212.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;assign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;posts_migrated_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;minus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;site&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;assign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;migration_percentage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;posts_migrated_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;divided_by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;times&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;round&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
&amp;lt;progress max=&quot;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;floor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&quot; 
    value=&quot;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;posts_migrated_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&quot; 
    title=&quot;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;migration_percentage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;% migrated&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/progress&amp;gt;
Migrated &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;posts_migrated_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;floor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; 
out of &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;total_post_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;floor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; posts migrated (&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;migration_percentage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;%&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;).  
&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;site&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; posts remaining to migrate.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-2020-08-27&quot;&gt;UPDATE 2020-08-27&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve finished the migration, migrating all of the 212 posts from my old blog, as such I’ve flipped the gauges that you see on this page and others to a fixed 100% complete gauge.  While this code worked very well, there’s no reason for it to be making additional math updates now that it is always going to come across as 100%.  The code snips above are still how to make the gauge dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Tech" /><category term="Coding" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="Liquid" /><category term="HTML5" /><category term="Guides" /><summary type="html">As I mentioned yesterday I’m moving posts over to Jekyll from my WordPress blog. To get started, I used a wordpress plugin called simply Jekyll Exporter to export all of my posts and pages into markdown files. This worked pretty well, but since I want my site to be 100% AMP Only, I decided that rather than just publishing them all I should make sure that none of the old markup (much of which has been migrated between 3 different platforms) ends up causing pages not to validate in the AMP Validator.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Migrating my blog and personal site to Jekyll</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/20/migrating-to-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Migrating my blog and personal site to Jekyll" /><published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/20/migrating-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/08/20/migrating-to-jekyll/">&lt;p&gt;After several years of using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wordpress.org&quot;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; as my blogging platform of choice, I’ve made the decision to move my personal site to &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll static site generator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-im-doing-this&quot;&gt;Why I’m doing this&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;super-fast&quot;&gt;Super Fast&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve blogged about on Justia’s Legal Marketing &amp;amp; Technology Blog several times, &lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2017/07/05/page-speed-tips-and-tools/&quot;&gt;web performance matters&lt;/a&gt;.  47% of users expect a web page to load in under 2 seconds, and 40% of users will abandon a page that takes longer than 3 seconds to load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WordPress is a fantastic blogging platform, and it is possible using a combination of best practices, extensive hosting infrastructure, and plugins such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/plugins/w3-total-cache/&quot;&gt;W3 Total Cache&lt;/a&gt; to make WordPress pages perform very well.  But nothing is faster than serving static files that require no server side code to view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I know quite a bit about optimizing WordPress, having done it for years, I’ve never bothered to spend any significant time optimizing this blog, and frankly it is not the best use of my time to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;infrastructure-light&quot;&gt;Infrastructure Light&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned that part of making a WordPress powered site perform optimally is having the server infrastructure in place to handle the demand.  This means a web server with plenty of CPU available for the code, and a MySQL server with plenty of CPU and Ram to handle requests quickly.  You then also have to be careful not to weigh your blog down with too many plugins that may impact performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my own personal site, which doesn’t make money, investing in this infrastructure to keep this site performing optimally would not be an efficient use of my money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub offers a free service called &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; which can host free static html sites on their servers.  While I’ve never had a problem running my own server (and still do for advanced projects), for my blog in particular I’d love to not have to worry about maintaining the server.  Since the output from jekyll is static html pages, the limitations of GitHub Pages (basically no server side code or database) are not a problem and it can handle this easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more is that GitHub pages supports jekyll natively, meaning that while I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; serve Jekyll pages anywhere on any web server, I don’t even have to run the builder to process the files when hosting them on GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coder-friendly&quot;&gt;Coder Friendly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a coder I’m comfortable working in &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;, especially the derivitive known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.github.com/gfm/&quot;&gt;GitHub Flavored Markdown&lt;/a&gt; which adds a number of coder friendly improvements over the top of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://spec.commonmark.org/current/&quot;&gt;CommonMark spec&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Jekyll sites are built from a markdown base (by default, you can also use plugins to build from other markup languages or just use plain html files) I’m able to author posts very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub Pages and &lt;abbr title=&quot;GitHub Flavored Markdown&quot;&gt;GFM&lt;/abbr&gt; allows me to integrate features from GitHub into my pages very simply.  For example I can easily &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/&quot;&gt;embed a gist&lt;/a&gt; in a page with a simple tag.  And I can insert code into my pages with syntax hilighting that matches the syntax hilighting on GitHub.  As like many developers I host my code repositories on GitHub, this makes it very easy to blog about my coding exploits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting feature of GitHub Pages is that I can &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/using-submodules-with-github-pages&quot;&gt;host documentation pages for my own GitHub hosted projects&lt;/a&gt; by using Git Submodules to embed the other github hosted repo in a subfolder of this.  As I work on more open source projects I intend on hosting my documentation on this site using this feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;version-controlled-site&quot;&gt;Version Controlled Site&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the idea of version controlling my live site, it allows me to see my edits over time.  This blog is now hosted on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nickmoline/nickmoline.github.io&quot;&gt;public repo&lt;/a&gt; on my GitHub account @nickmoline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes it very easy to track what changes I’ve made over time, both to the layout of the site and even the content of individual pages.  It allows me all of the power of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; Version Control System over my own content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-still-love-wordpress&quot;&gt;I still love WordPress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought about doing this many times over the years.  What held me back is that I happen to love WordPress.  I’m not alone in this, as of the time I’m writing this, &lt;a href=&quot;https://w3techs.com/technologies/details/cm-wordpress&quot;&gt;38.1% of all websites are hosted on WordPress&lt;/a&gt; accounting for 63.5% of websites hosted by a known &lt;abbr title=&quot;Content Management System&quot;&gt;CMS&lt;/abbr&gt; according to W3techs.  When over a third of all websites in the world are powered by WordPress, there is a good reason for that.  WordPress is extremely flexible allowing you to host any type of website from a blog like this one to a fully fledged eCommerce site using freely available plugins to add functionality needed for a particular site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still use WordPress in a number of projects both for work and for personal side projects such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hp-lexicon.org/&quot;&gt;The Harry Potter Lexicon&lt;/a&gt; and the website for &lt;a href=&quot;https://sunnyvaleplayers.org&quot;&gt;Sunnyvale Community Players&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;migration-progress&quot;&gt;Migration Progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than dump all of the posts at once, I’m taking the time to go through the posts and fix the formatting to match the new layout.  For your amusement, here is the migration progress statistics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;progress max=&quot;212&quot; value=&quot;212.0&quot; title=&quot;100.0% migrated&quot;&gt;&lt;/progress&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Migrated &lt;strong&gt;212&lt;/strong&gt; out of &lt;strong&gt;212&lt;/strong&gt; posts migrated (&lt;strong&gt;100.0%&lt;/strong&gt;).  &lt;strong&gt;0&lt;/strong&gt; posts remaining to migrate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Web" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="GitHub" /><category term="WordPress" /><category term="Markdown" /><summary type="html">After several years of using Wordpress as my blogging platform of choice, I’ve made the decision to move my personal site to Jekyll static site generator.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Personality Test 2020</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/07/10/personality-test" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personality Test 2020" /><published>2020-07-10T15:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/07/10/personality-test-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2020/07/10/personality-test">&lt;p&gt;This morning as a team building exercise, the Engineering Team at Justia took personality tests at the website &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/rx7hf4vd2isxptg/Screen%20Shot%202020-08-26%20at%201.08.18%20PM.png?dl=0&quot;&gt;16 Personalities&lt;/a&gt; and shared our results.  In the early days of this blog (was called Cap’s Log back then) I took some online &lt;a href=&quot;/tags/#personality-test&quot;&gt;personality tests&lt;/a&gt; from time to time and posted my results here, so I thought I’d do the same here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a much more modern take on the Personality Test system than the ones I did between 2003 and &lt;a href=&quot;/2006/05/30/personality-test/&quot;&gt;2006&lt;/a&gt;.  Instead of focusing on a large number of attributes they focus on 5 characteristic pairs, and represent each pair as scale between the 2 extremes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pairs are categorized as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mind:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Introverted&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;Extroverted&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energy:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Intuitive&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;Observant&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nature:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Thinking&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;Feeling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tactics:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Judging&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;Prospecting&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Assertive&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;Turbulent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They then summarize these attributes into one of 16 personality types (hense the name), a code, a role, and a strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking the test I was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/profiles/4f9a7cf0b6da1&quot;&gt;graded overall&lt;/a&gt; as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Type:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Turbulent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/infp-personality&quot;&gt;Mediator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Code:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;INFP-T&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Role:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/roles-diplomats&quot;&gt;Diplomat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Strategy:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/strategies-constant-improvement&quot;&gt;Constant Improvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mind-introverted-82&quot;&gt;Mind: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/mind-introverted-vs-extraverted&quot;&gt;Introverted&lt;/a&gt; (82%)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mind category is the one personality characteristic everyone knows, “Introverted” vs “Extroverted.”  I’m not surprised to find out that I’m graded as mostly an Introvert, &lt;strong&gt;82% &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/mind-introverted-vs-extraverted&quot;&gt;Introverted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and 18% Extroverted.  Being an introvert doesn’t mean I don’t like people or that I don’t like being around people, quite the contrary.  As an Introvert I make a relatively few friendships but those friendships I do cultivate are very deep friendships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy-intuitive-73&quot;&gt;Energy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/energy-intuitive-vs-observant&quot;&gt;Intuitive&lt;/a&gt; (73%)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the energy category I came out as &lt;strong&gt;73% &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/energy-intuitive-vs-observant&quot;&gt;Intuitive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and 27% Observant.  An Intuitive person is described as being imaginative, open minded, and curious.  I think this describes me very well.  When I’m faced with a challenge, I look at things from multiple angles, keeping an open mind, and am able to come up with creative and inventive solutions to problems.  I also love when I’m faced with something new, which really does energize me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nature-feeling-86&quot;&gt;Nature: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/nature-thinking-vs-feeling&quot;&gt;Feeling&lt;/a&gt; (86%)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one surprised me a bit.  At &lt;strong&gt;86% &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/nature-thinking-vs-feeling&quot;&gt;Feeling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; versus only 14% Thinking, I clearly come across as more emotional than I expected.  The description however does make sense.  I am generally sensitive to what people are thinking and I can’t stand people putting each other down competitively rather than working together cooperatively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tactics-prospecting-61&quot;&gt;Tactics: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/tactics-judging-vs-prospecting&quot;&gt;Prospecting&lt;/a&gt; (61%)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the other categories, I’m much closer to the center on this.  My &lt;strong&gt;61% &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/tactics-judging-vs-prospecting&quot;&gt;Prospecting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; score still clearly beats out the 39% Judging, but I think I do have aspects of both in this.  In general Prospecting individuals are good at improvisation and spotting opportunities.  It is my ability to be flexible that is one of my strongest traits, as well as my strongest weakness.  Fortunately I do have a fairly strong Judging trait as well, which insists on getting things right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;identity-turbulent-90&quot;&gt;Identity: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/identity-assertive-vs-turbulent&quot;&gt;Turbulent&lt;/a&gt; (90%)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is no contest.  &lt;strong&gt;90% &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/identity-assertive-vs-turbulent&quot;&gt;Turbulent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; easily demolishes the 10% Assertive.  I feel this is something I need to actually work on, be slightly less Turbulent (which is self conscious and sensitive to stress) and be more Assertive (self assured and resistant to stress).  I insist on success and when I fail (which I do) I beat myself up about it, which raises my stress level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;life-as-a-mediator&quot;&gt;Life as a Mediator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;ntroverted I&lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;tuitive &lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt;eeling &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;rospecting life of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/infp-personality&quot;&gt;Mediator&lt;/a&gt; means I always want to find the good in people, and I want to help others succeed, and this is true about me.  I’m creative and filled with passion, guided by my principles.  I’m a perfectionist who wants things to be perfect and works to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite parts of the personality assessment is where it compares my results with famous real and fictional people to indicate others who share characteristics like me.  Other historical and celebrity &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/infp-personality&quot;&gt;Mediator&lt;/a&gt;s include William Shakespeare, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/jrr-tolkien-creator-of-words-and-worlds-the-lord-of-the-rings-personality-series&quot;&gt;J.R.R. Tolkien&lt;/a&gt;, Johnny Depp, and Julia Roberts.  Fictional Characters who match the Mediator personality type include both Frodo Baggins and Arwen from &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;, Anne from &lt;em&gt;Anne of Green Gables&lt;/em&gt;, and Fox Mulder from &lt;em&gt;The X-Files&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some thought I can see how these people, both real and imagined, have characteristics that match me, and perhaps it is why I’m drawn to some of these specific characters often.  In the &lt;em&gt;Rings&lt;/em&gt; Trilogy I’m drawn to Arwen more than any of the other elves (even &lt;em&gt;Elrond&lt;/em&gt;), and while I thought my reason for being fascinated with Frodo was because he is the central character, I realize it is really because of the way he acts in situations being familiar to me.  And with Tolkien being a Mediator as well, it makes sense that his central character would have similar characteristics.  Shakespeare was the master of understanding the emotion behind his characters.  And in a similar way Johnny Depp is so creative and quirky, he chooses roles that require him to express emotion, his characters all tend to be loners (Introverts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;life-as-a-turbulent-mediator&quot;&gt;Life as a Turbulent Mediator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/identity-assertive-vs-turbulent&quot;&gt;Turbulent&lt;/a&gt; trait on top of the Mediator means I am driven by success not just for me but for others as well, and I don’t take failure well.  This is true and something I need to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an interesting experiment to take this personality disorder quiz and see how I stacked up against my colleagues.  I’ll have to take this again sometime and see if any of those percentages have changed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Life" /><category term="Personality Test" /><category term="Justia" /><category term="Team Building" /><summary type="html">This morning as a team building exercise, the Engineering Team at Justia took personality tests at the website 16 Personalities and shared our results. In the early days of this blog (was called Cap’s Log back then) I took some online personality tests from time to time and posted my results here, so I thought I’d do the same here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Google I/O 2019 Experience</title><link href="https://www.nickmoline.com/2019/05/30/google-io-2019-io19/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Google I/O 2019 Experience" /><published>2019-05-30T23:30:57+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T04:30:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nickmoline.com/2019/05/30/google-io-2019-io19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nickmoline.com/2019/05/30/google-io-2019-io19/">&lt;p&gt;Barbara and I attended the Google I/O 2019 developer conference earlier this month. We’ve attended the conference every year since the first in 2008. I also attended its predecessor, the original &lt;a href=&quot;/2007/06/03/google-developer-day-2007/&quot;&gt;Google Developer Day&lt;/a&gt; the year before. This marks my 13th annual general Google Developer conference, and my 12th Google I/O specifically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google keeps altering the form a bit. In 2016 they moved the conference from being an indoor conference at Moscone Center in San Francisco to a mostly outdoor “festival” at the Shoreline Amphitheatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still not a fan of the outdoor festival over the indoor conference, as it presents a number of problems. These problems include: sunburn, pushing the wheelchair all over the place over uneven terrain, and lack of power outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They continue to learn from each year’s conference and make adjustments that fix some of the larger problems. For example after the first year, sunscreen was provided everywhere throughout the conference to help with the sunburn problems. They also made session rooms larger and introduced a reservation system so that people didn’t have to wait for sessions out in the sun for long periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t cover the big announcements from Google I/O 2019 in this post. &lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2019/05/30/thoughts-from-google-i-o-2019/&quot;&gt;I covered them over on Justia’s blog&lt;/a&gt;. There are, however, some things I wanted to cover that I couldn’t really cover on the other blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;particularly-inspiring-sessions-from-google-io-2019&quot;&gt;Particularly Inspiring Sessions from Google I/O 2019&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, there was a change in the focus of a lot of the sessions. There were still sessions about changed Google APIs and products and how to use them. But, there were also a number of sessions that were there to inspire developers to make great things. Some of them didn’t even have to do with Google services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the sessions from Google I/O 2019 that I found the most inspiring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teaching-a-car-to-drive-itself-by-imitation-and-imagination&quot;&gt;Teaching a Car to Drive Itself by Imitation and Imagination&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;amp-youtube data-videoid=&quot;mxqdVO462HU&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-youtube&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching a Car to Drive Itself by Imitation and Imagination&lt;/strong&gt; was a session hosted by Mayank Bansal of &lt;a href=&quot;https://waymo.com/&quot;&gt;Waymo&lt;/a&gt;. I wasn’t sure what to expect from this session, since Waymo doesn’t yet have any public APIs or services a developer could use. I wasn’t expecting the session to be a deep dive into explaining the process that the Waymo team followed to train the machine learning models that allow their self driving cars to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He explained the pitfalls that the team came across when doing the project, and didn’t shy away from the ways the team failed in their early attempts. This was an absolutely fascinating session, and extremely inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stadia-streaming-tech-a-deep-dive&quot;&gt;Stadia Streaming Tech: A Deep Dive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;amp-youtube data-videoid=&quot;9Htdhz6Op1I&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-youtube&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This session pleasantly surprised me as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.google.com/us/magazine/stadia?hl=en-US&quot;&gt;Stadia&lt;/a&gt; is Google’s new Streaming Gaming product that will come out later this year (announced back at the Game Developer Conference earlier this year). I assumed this session would be aimed at game developers wanting to develop for the service. Instead, the session was a deep dive into streaming technology as a whole and just how they changed the way streaming video works to reduce latency as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It went into the fundamentals of how streaming has worked historically and how they have changed it to fit this particular use case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sound-design-and-sonic-brand&quot;&gt;Sound Design and Sonic Brand&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;amp-youtube data-videoid=&quot;r6Nzqcotujc&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-youtube&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to being a Software Engineer at Justia, I also work with a non-profit Community Theater group called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sunnyvaleplayers.org/&quot;&gt;Sunnyvale Community Players&lt;/a&gt;. I help SCP put on several musical theater productions a year. On most shows I’ve worked on, I work as either a Sound Designer or a Sound Engineer. As such, when I saw a session about Sound Design on the agenda for Google I/O 2019, I didn’t hesitate a second to reserve my spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This session was a fantastic session on Sonic Branding and creating sound effects and I for one found it particularly interesting. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/conor&quot;&gt;Conor O’Sullivan&lt;/a&gt; is a sound designer at Google and is responsible for a lot of the sounds that you barely notice but are crucial to your google experience. Things like the boot up sound on Google home, or all the clicks, boops, beeps and whistles you hear when using an Android phone or a Google app on any phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session was filled with guidelines on how to approach sound design for a product, which is a bit different than sound design for a musical, but many of the same rules apply. Google has compiled these guidelines and more into a set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://material.io/design/sound/&quot;&gt;Material Sound Design&lt;/a&gt; guidelines which is excellent reading (and listening) for anyone working with sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-creativity-and-technology-with-legendary-animator-glen-keane&quot;&gt;On Creativity and Technology, with Legendary Animator Glen Keane&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;amp-youtube data-videoid=&quot;qL4U9Ygtxh8&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-youtube&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a very personal report from former Disney animator &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glen_Keane&quot;&gt;Glen Keane&lt;/a&gt;, explaining how someone most known for using a pencil and paper to create characters such as Ariel (from &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;) and the Beast (from &lt;em&gt;Beauty and the Beast&lt;/em&gt;) could learn to embrace technology and demonstrating how technology fosters creativity. The session was deeply moving, and it was powerful just being in the same room as this incredibly creative individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fan of both Technology and Disney Animation, this was definitely a session that I was excited about. I unfortunately got there late because of traffic, but I’ve rewatched the video to catch what I missed, and now so can you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;michio-kaku-on-the-future-of-humanity&quot;&gt;Michio Kaku on the Future of Humanity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;amp-youtube data-videoid=&quot;zsnc0vkwWRk&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-youtube&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sessions don’t get any more inspiring this session with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michio_Kaku&quot;&gt;Michio Kaku&lt;/a&gt;, the co-founder of String Field Theory and one of the most intelligent people in the world. This interview and Q&amp;amp;A session left everyone in the room thinking about what the future holds, not just with technology, but with the mind, education, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A massive standing ovation ended the session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-google-io-2019-live-blogs&quot;&gt;My Google I/O 2019 Live Blogs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I live blogged 7 sessions for Justia’s Legal Marketing &amp;amp; Technology Blog. I started doing this 2 years ago at Google I/O 2017. I used a different service this year from years past. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arena.im&quot;&gt;arena.im&lt;/a&gt; service I tried out this year actually has an AMP compatible embed, so for the first time the live blogs could work in AMP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the sessions from Google I/O 2019 I live blogged:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2019/05/07/building-successful-websites-case-studies-for-mature-and-emerging-markets-io19-live-blogs/&quot;&gt;Building Successful Websites: Case Studies for Mature and Emerging Markets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2019/05/08/enhance-your-search-and-assistant-presence-with-structured-data-io19-live-blogs/&quot;&gt;Enhance Your Search and Assistant Presence with Structured Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2019/05/08/rapidly-building-better-web-experiences-with-amp-io19-live-blogs/&quot;&gt;Rapidly Building Better Web Experiences with AMP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2019/05/08/speed-at-scale-web-performance-tips-and-tricks-from-the-trenches-io19-live-blogs/&quot;&gt;Speed at Scale: Web Performance Tips and Tricks from the Trenches&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2019/05/09/google-search-state-of-the-union-io19-live-blogs/&quot;&gt;Google Search: State of the Union&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2019/05/09/amp-for-email-coming-soon-to-an-inbox-near-you/&quot;&gt;AMP for Email: Coming Soon to an Inbox Near You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onward.justia.com/2019/05/09/google-search-and-javascript-sites-io19-live-blogs/&quot;&gt;Google Search and JavaScript Sites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thoughts-on-the-arenaim-service&quot;&gt;Thoughts on the arena.im service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;arena.im also had an advantage in that it had a pretty good mobile app. I had Barbara take pictures for me while I focused on taking notes. Barbara signed into the app on her own phone while I signed in on my laptop to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service also had a nifty feature that allowed me to connect my twitter account. Whenever I would tweet something with the #io19 hashtag during one of my live blog sessions, it would automatically post the tweet into the live stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall arena.im worked well, though I did have problems in one of the sessions. About a third of the way through the session, the twitter feature malfunctioned. Instead of just posting &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; tweets with the #io19 hashtag, it was posting tweets from anyone using the #io19 hashtag. What’s more, turning the feature off wouldn’t stop the deluge. I spent most of my time during that session deleting tweets from the live stream that shouldn’t have been there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that issue, I disabled the automatic posting of tweets feature for the rest of the conference. Instead, I had it pull up a stream of tweets in a panel. Whenever I would tweet something that I wanted to also post, I’d hit the post button from there. This way I was in control of what ended up in the liveblog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-could-be-better&quot;&gt;What could be better&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked arena.im and I’d probably use it again, but I wish I could find a service that would handle the AMP embed using &lt;a href=&quot;https://amp.dev/documentation/components/amp-live-list&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;amp-live-list&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; instead of just using &lt;a href=&quot;https://amp.dev/documentation/components/amp-iframe&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;amp-iframe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. With &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;amp-live-list&lt;/code&gt; the entire live blog post would be AMP and I could actually style the output to meet my needs. Also arena.im doesn’t seem to have an export feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an event, I like to turn my live-blogs into normal blog posts that don’t need external resources to work. This is generally better for SEO and it is faster to load and easier to style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve started converting my live blogs from this year. It is slow going, though, since I have to manually re-create the stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts-from-google-io-2019&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts from Google I/O 2019&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2019/05/MVIMG_20190507_083220-1-e1559243854902.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Nick and Barbara showing their Google Fandom as they wait for the Google I/O 2019 Keynote to begin&quot; width=&quot;2519&quot; height=&quot;1572&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2019/05/MVIMG_20190507_083220-1-e1559243854902.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nick and Barbara showing their Google Fandom as they wait for the Google I/O 2019 Keynote to begin&quot; width=&quot;2519&quot; height=&quot;1572&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google I/O is a high point of my year, every year for the last 13 years. I show my excitement for it by doing crazy things like coloring my hair. Barbara even does face paint to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s conference felt different from recent years past. I still got sun burned in spite of tons of sunscreen. Yes, I still ended each day so exhausted that I could barely walk to my bedroom. But it has been a long time since I’ve left Google I/O feeling so inspired. Inspired to make great things, to push the future of technology, and to follow that great adage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;amp-img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2019/05/MVIMG_20190507_093246-1.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The quote &amp;quot;If at first you don't succeed, sudo&amp;quot; appeared on the main screen as we waited for the Google I/O 2019 Keynote address&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;amp-img fallback=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2019/05/MVIMG_20190507_093246-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The quote &amp;quot;If at first you don't succeed, sudo&amp;quot; appeared on the main screen as we waited for the Google I/O 2019 Keynote address&quot; width=&quot;4032&quot; height=&quot;3024&quot; layout=&quot;responsive&quot; lightbox=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/amp-img&gt;
&lt;/amp-img&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never give up. Push the limits of creativity and animation like Glen Keane. Teach a car to drive itself like Waymo. Solve the greatest mysteries of the universe like Michio Kaku. Whatever you do, keep moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time at Google I/O 2019 and I’m looking forward to Google I/O 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Moline</name></author><category term="Tech" /><category term="Events" /><category term="Writing" /><category term="Google I/O" /><category term="Conference" /><category term="Waymo" /><category term="Google" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Stadia" /><category term="Sound Design" /><category term="AMP" /><category term="Justia" /><category term="Onward Blog" /><summary type="html">Barbara and I attended the Google I/O 2019 developer conference earlier this month. We’ve attended the conference every year since the first in 2008. I also attended its predecessor, the original Google Developer Day the year before. This marks my 13th annual general Google Developer conference, and my 12th Google I/O specifically.</summary></entry></feed>